[Music]
hi welcome back you're watching trading
hour and it's over to manisha now who
joins in to talk about what's buzzing in
the commodity space and it's coffee so
good morning to all of us
oh well yes uh it's four and a half
percent higher in sense of prices this
week it's alone so i'm really going to
put some numbers across to you on what
to watch out in sense of copy coffee and
why are we looking at a deficit in this
year well to begin with we're looking at
prices on the higher side because of the
tight supply concerns especially in
brazil which is the biggest producer and
exporter for coffee as well and then
you're looking at prices moderating
after the hitting those 10-year highs in
the month of feb but you know most of
the concerns have still continued to be
on whether it is the high input prices
whether it is the shipping container
availability and higher energy prices
markets also have seen some concerns
because arising out of russia and
ukraine and that is what we'll talk
about as well but the supportive factors
first and the chinese 2022 imports are
expected to increase by 5 to nearly 4
million bags and then when you look at
colombia which is the second largest
producer for coffee the march exports
declined by nearly 13
so that tells you that the inventories
or the supplies haven't gained but the
demand continues to be on the stronger
side the russia ukraine demand is
something that is concerning because
russia is one a big coffee drinking
nation and one million bags of a decline
in russian demand is what the world is
working with apart from that the vietnam
exports also have seen an increase up by
nearly 19 and the strength in us dollar
nearly at a two year highs is yet
another thing that is keeping the prices
in control right now
take a look at what the markets are
anticipating in sense of brazil exports
last year was 45.67 million bags this
time around is 33.2 so lower
availability from brazil is one of the
major factors that has been supportive
for prices i also want to put across on
what we are looking at in sense of
deficit this year so the international
coffee organization believes that we're
looking at 3.1 million bag offer deficit
but hedgepoint another trader believes
that we are looking at a much higher
deficit for the same year at around 7.2
million bags and they believe that the
next year you could be looking at a
surplus of 1.2 billion bags because of
the higher prices and the weather
getting better you could be looking at a
better coffee crop as well but when you
look at the global production and
consumption numbers that will tell you
on how the on why rather the coffee
prices will be trading positive in this
year so this is last year where you saw
higher production but lower consumption
this year we're looking at numbers
actually reversing you're looking at a
lower production but much higher
consumption and that is the reason we
are looking at that deficit for the
indian markets as well we've seen coffee
prices continue to gain up because we
have seen our exports gain up by 42
this is a record number by the way so
whether you look at international
markets or the indian markets the coffee
prices are set to rise at least for this
year manisha thank you very much for
that the message i got on a monday
morning was that i don't need an
inspirational court to get through today
i need coffee